we're going to look at how you can
actually identify informative trading
activity by looking at the tick-by-tick
trade level data we're going to use an
algorithm called the bulk volume
classification algorithm which is used
to aggregate a number of Trades to then
understand the trade flow and classify
whether there's a predominant buy or
sell signal this could possibly be used
for a momentum type indicator or to help
market makers understand the risk and
how to adjust pricing so how are we
going to get this trade level
tick-by-tick data well we're going to be
utilizing the Theta data API this is an
API where we can get either historical
data or stream real-time trades when you
specify the parameters correctly you can
actually get back the last quote at the
time of trade which is really helpful
when you're trying to implement some of
these algorithms so let's understand
some of the background of this why would
we care what information based trading
activity is and why would you need to
know about it well essentially an
informed Trader is just a Trader who
knows something private information
either good news and wants to profit by
buying while Traders with bad news will
want to profit by selling so why do we
care well essentially in the market
microstructure models trade data has
historically played a very big role in
trying to understand and provide a
signal for this underlying private
information so for example the trade
imbalance which is just the difference
between the buys and sells signal that
liquidity pressure can lead to
subsequent price movements this can be
caused by example for an informed Trader
who knows something transacting in very
large volumes in a particular direction
therefore it would be very advantageous
to be able to detect this Infamous
informative trading activity and
therefore potentially the market maker
or the investor then could adjust their
bids their offers accordingly so through
information detective one a primary goal
is obviously to actually understand
whether there is informative trading
activity but the other consideration is
actually trying to assign for each
particular trade whether it was
aggressor initiated so what do we mean
by that we mean was it initiated by the
buyer or the seller and we would like to
know this information because it can be
useful in trying to assess trading costs
and implementing your trading costs
algorithm so traditional approaches at
this in the past were trying to attempt
to identify individual trades as the
aggressor so who is the buyer who was
the seller if this information wasn't
provided available from the exchanges so
the most established algorithms that
have been implemented to try and
identify the aggressor have been the
lien ready so LR the emo and the clnv
and these classified trades based on the
proximity of the transaction price to
the quotes that were in effect at the
time of the trade however in today's
market this is very problematic because
we have increased frequency of order
submission canceling and across multiple
exchanges so this is a problem the
complication of using these historical
algorithms is that it's very difficult
to do this in the high frequency World
in a new world of electronic markets
we've got complex order types we've got
Market fragmentation where orders are
split across exchanges and we've got
high frequency order cancellations we've
got complex order execution algorithms
which can split parent orders into
numerous children and distribute them
across different platforms with
different order types so in summary it
can be very hard to say that the
consolidation tape which is the final
take that has the trade summary is
actually in the correct order
and it's very hard to understand whether
with such high cancellation rates even
one of these papers quotes up to 98
complicates actually knowing the true
actual quotes at the time of historical
trades so trade classification
algorithms of the which that we've just
spoke about that are highly reliant on
the
um order book and the Consolidated tape
being in the correct sequence are
severely compromised so they're the
rules based on the upticks and the
downticks and the proximity to bid and
ask quotes because of the high
cancellation rates of those orders so
both research papers that I have down in
the bottom in the description below have
found that the traditional algorithms
find that individual trade assessor no
longer captures informative based
trading so traditional algorithms fail
to explain the Dynamics of the spread
and price over time and this suggests
that other sources of buying and selling
pressure are ignored by these tick based
rules we've just been over so what's the
solution well essentially a easily at
all came up with the bulk volume
classification algorithm so bvc which is
instead tries to classify these
individual trades as aggregator trades
by either volume or ticks and then
they're going to infer the buy and
selling activities from this Collective
group
so the bvc algorithm therefore focuses
on classification of these aggregated
trade flows which is then less dependent
on the actual order of the book
so because bvc uses the market makers
aggregated response to the order flow to
infer its informational content it
therefore overcomes these limitations as
we've moved into this high frequency
trading world and both these papers have
found that BBC can identify trade
aggressors as well as traditional
algorithms and it's signed order flow as
is the only measure that is reliably
related to different liquidity measures
such as open interest and spread so
these two papers that I have Linked In
the description are very informative I
recommend taking a look into it and also
I've put some more research into my
Jupiter notebook about the scientific
method and the regression that they did
to come up with this to prove their
hypothesis so our aim today is to
actually just implement the BBC
algorithm using the data that we're
getting from Theta data historically in
future videos I want to try and use and
develop this algorithm so we can include
it in real time streaming which is
available through data data and also I
plan on doing a series that focuses on
developing on creating a market making
trading bot and we could possibly
incorporate this information as a risk
metric first off let's start with our
Imports we've got OS time pickle random
numpy pandas plat matplotlib for
plotting date time and Theta data
classes here my code will be available
in the Jupiter books within my patreon
page
so getting the data this is the first
step so Theta data is this API where we
can get either real-time or historical
nbb option data so Nation Nationals best
bid an offer or request historical data
and trades and quotes up for 10 years so
let's get
um all the expirations on a particular
underline so the first thing we're going
to do we're going to provide our Theta
data username and password I have mine
cased here in a DOT Enviro in file so
you would just place your username and
password here and I've created this
function for a get expirations so based
on a ticker we're going to get all our
expirations
so now that for Microsoft I have all of
the expirations available by Theta data
and you can see back to 10 years
um 2012 all the way to through to 2025.
so now I want to actually get all the
strikes for all these options so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to create a
get strikes function where we can pass
it our root ticker and our expiration
dates and what we're going to get back
is a dictionary with the keys there's
all the expression dates of all the
strikes available on that option
so I've actually I won't run that now
I've pickled the data so we can have
access to it and as you can see
um here is all the strikes on just a
particular expiration that I've chosen
at random so we have to pre-process the
expiration so we can actually just get a
subset of the expiration dates um
because Theta data is very inclusive and
it has all the information traded and
particular exchanges we're getting
weeklies and less traded options what we
want to do competitive market makers and
primary market makers are mostly going
to be on
um and obliged to show quotes on the
actively traded monthly option Series so
all I've got here is a function that's
going to return the monthly expiration
so the third Friday and every month
expiries so then we get a subset of our
expirations back called month
expirations
so the fourth step in this first stage
is get all the data for a particular
contract and Strikes so here now I'm
choosing a particular contract so I'm
going to choose a call and I'm going to
say Microsoft at a particular expiration
date I'm going to give it a whole bunch
of strikes and then I'm going to choose
all the call options and I want to get
the historical trading period between a
start date and an end date
so here all I'm doing is I'm going to
store the data in a dictionary I'm using
the the connecting to the Theta data
terminal and then I'm looping through my
strikes and attempting to get the
historical information so client dot get
historical information I want the trade
quote level information between
particular dates for a strike
if the data is not there then I want to
throw an exception and then I'm also
going to store that as an n a
so
once I've been through that process I
then have my strikes so I've chosen this
particular expiry date so here I've got
June the 16th and here are all my
strikes that I've returned information
back
so again I won't execute this I've
pickled the information so we can take a
look at all the trade activities so for
all the strikes you can see here are the
number of Trades that have been passed
and essentially what I'm going to do I'm
just going to choose the most actively
traded one over the last six months and
I think it's this one here
it is the 300 strike so 17 835
um options traded so I can pass that
back as a data frame and then we're just
gonna we're gonna rename that subsection
of the dictionary as the single data
frame trades underscore DF so we get our
Theta data dictionary back what I want
to do now is we're going to take a look
at individual trades level information
and we notice that we've got this Ms of
day and date column separated so I
actually want to just simplify that and
combine it so that we can have a date as
an index which is much easier so we're
going to do a bit of data processing I'm
going to take those dates and the
milliseconds of the day and add that to
something called date time new column I
also want the value of the trade which
is just the price times the size I also
want the volume order which is uh just
the size rank so
essentially I'm going to Resort my data
frame and then I want to drop some of
these excess columns that I no longer
need anymore
I also want to include some of the nums
that Theta data provides within their
num classes so we've got some trade
types here I've got the trade condition
and I've also got exchanges so I'm just
creating dictionaries for those and nums
um and getting the keys as the values
and the names and then I'm just going to
substitute them within my data frame
here I'm just grouping on the conditions
so you can see the conditions and the
amounts of trades for this particular
option series and the sizes that were
executed so auto execution into Market
sweeps Opera X towers and you can look
at the difference between these types of
trade conditions on the actual NASDAQ
website
um so we also want to look at the
different types of exchanges so again in
the modern day we have multiple
exchanges that are trading the exact
same product so it's interesting to be
able to look at the bid exchange look at
the ask exchange and again they're
stored in the nums so I'm creating a new
column and applying that formula so I
can get those columns I'm grouping back
just for example on the bid exchange so
we can see the different exchanges where
these options were traded and in what
volumes so now I have my final data
frame ready for actual analysis so again
we've got the size the price and I have
the quote level information of the last
quote that was available
um at the time of the trade but again
remember we don't know if that was the
true quote before there because there is
such a high level of cancellation within
the water order books across exchanges
so this is really helpful and can use
can be utilized for a whole bunch of
analysis however
uh we're looking for really reliable and
across time dependency and in the New
Market that's what this uh bulk volume
classification algorithm and aggregated
trade level is useful for for the bulk
volume classification algorithm we have
a timer volume bar for time Tau so this
is assigned a price change so Delta P
between those two time periods and
essentially we want to let these two
variables so hat volume Tau buy and hat
volume Tau sell equal to the following
so we have VT which is the volume traded
in that specific interval and either the
volume bar or the time bar and then we
have it multiplied by T which is our CDF
of the student T distribution with DF
degrees Freedom so our Z variable here
our variable for the student T
distribution is the difference between
the price so the magnitude change
divided by the sigma which is the
volatility of that particular
trading interval so here that's just
giving a standardized magnitude of the
movement that occurred between that time
bar so we're using the student T
distribution to be able to provide a
factor for that and awaiting
so the formula that we're going to use
for the volume weighted standard
deviation of price is the following and
we're going to have to use a look back
period that we can Define within our
equation to get that standard trailing
standard deviation over this is
consistent with the two papers that we
referenced before
so examples of this so volumes are
therefore assigned a direction of price
changes and a magnitude so the volumes
will be weighted depending on how large
the price change is in absolute term so
in magnitude and then the this is
relative to the distribution of those
price changes so for example if we have
no price change then the total volume
Trader will be equally split between
buyers and cells if the price change is
greater than zero then the volume
weighted is more towards buys and sells
and then vice versa for Price decrease
so it's more weighted to sales so let's
look at writing the function and writing
the bulk volume classification so we're
going to need that roll back look back
standard deviation so here we're going
to pass the price difference series and
here we're going to have a look back
period n so
if the length of the price difference is
less than that window then I want to
throw a value error look back window is
greater than the rows for data frame
just so the user knows what's going on
if not we're going to return the price
difference dot rolling window equals
that n look back period and then we're
going to go dot standard deviation so
using Panda's internal functions there
so for the bulk volume classification if
classifier we're going to have this
algorithm and it's going to take in
appendix data frame which is going to be
a bar we don't know if it's a timer
volume bar but it is going to contain
open high low close and the volume
traded within that time period we're
also going to give it an integer a look
back period and we're also going to give
it degrees of freedom for the student T
distribution we're going to get back a
data frame so we're going to calculate
first the change in price over that data
period and all we need to do for that is
to find a Delta P which will be a panda
series and we're just going to take the
difference between the close prices and
all I need to do here is take the data
series Dot close and minus against the
shifted data series Dot close then we
can calculate the standard deviation
across those periods with that specific
Look Back by passing our Delta P into
the function and our look back period
into the function that we defined before
the Z variable for our student T
distribution is just that Delta P then
divided by our Sigma p and then we can
assign and get the weight by that
student T distribution by using the
scipy stats module so sci-fi
stats.t.cdf and we're going to pass that
Z variable and the degrees of freedom
so once we've got that weighted picture
like a weighted average we're going to
calculate VB hat and vs hat individually
so we're just going to take that volume
series for our bars and multiply it by X
and that's going to be the assignment to
the buy and then it's just 1 minus that
for the cells
so then I'm just going to rename those
series and then we're going to
concatenate them and we're also going to
create another column called volume
fraction which is just going to be the
fraction of buys compared to the volume
traded total we need to actually pass a
bar so either volume or tick bar let's
explain what those are first we need to
create a helper function to allow us to
construct and return an integer number
of bars I've actually been through this
in a machine learning video before using
the practices that Marcos Lopez de predo
has implemented within his machine
advances in machine learning book so if
you're interested in learning more about
tick bars volume bars please take a look
at that video link in the description so
here we've got a bar and we're going to
take an X and Y and we're going to
return an integer number of bars we're
going to use this to construct our tick
bars and we want to sample the variables
open high low close from within a
specific number of transactions so tick
bars we specifying number of
transactions like five trades or ten
trades 20 trades number of Trades and we
want to pass the trades level data that
we have before from our data frame so
that's the trades underscore DF
so specifying the number of transactions
and all I'm going to do is I'm going to
assign the number of bars which is
dependent on the length of my trading
frame and then the number of
transactions so I'm then going to
aggregate
um my data price information to open
high low close
and I'm also going to do the sum of the
size which will be the volume so now
that we have that information all I'm
going to do is then create a new one
called volume which is just going to
bring in that original Theta data
information on the size and pass that
out as our tip bars so we there we've
created our tick bars here I've just
plotted what that looks like with a
histogram and you can see the
distribution there over our six month
period for that particular option trade
so here we've got volume bars so volume
bars are sampled at a predefined amount
of traded volume so here we're doing the
exact same thing we're passing in a
volume though instead of a transaction
number and then again we're creating our
bar based on the cumulative sum of the
trading size and the volume that we're
specifying that we want to create the
bars over again we're aggregating the
same information price open high low
close and we're also getting the sum of
the trading data back but it's now
negligible because we're actually
assigning what that value is so we're
getting we're just saying that the
volume traded equals 10 here and you can
see the distribution here so now I
actually want to implement and classify
our trades that we've got from our data
data API so let's create tick bars and
volume bars use whichever one you want
and then we're going to pass that
through to our bulk volume classifier so
our open high low close volume bars is
going to be equal to tick bars
and we're going to assign a look back
for the standard deviation of 100
periods
100 bars here I'm just then printing the
information
and you can see I'm adding the close
information into our BBC appendix data
frame because we're going to use that
for plotting so essentially I get back
my bulk volume classify information as
the buys the cell volumes and then the
fraction of buys versus total volume and
the close information now how let's
actually visualize these results and see
how this can help us potentially or a
market maker in making informed
decisions and potentially adjusting
strategies so let's look at a subsection
of the data the last 100 data points and
here I'm plotting in the graph in the
blue uh the the fraction of buys that
were greater than 0.5 in blue and then
in red I'm doing the fraction of buys
that so more certain more orientated
towards selling volume in red here in
the black line which is on the Y2 axis
here is price so here you can see the
movement and we have the corresponding
index of bars and the colors of our
fraction of buys now this is a little
bit hard to see visually because there
are even 100 data points is hard to see
but in both of those papers they
established that there is correlation
and regression capability of this
indicator to indicate a relationship
towards future spread volatility and
open interest and this can be linked to
then Market aversion and volatility so
this is very important for market makers
and can be used as a really good
indicator now let's just take a quick
look into what that could look like so
creating an indicator potentially right
now we have this fraction of buyers so
which is between zero and one
with the uh you know equal volumes of
buys and sells being 0.5 it might be
more useful if we had an indicator for
example to be between -1 in heavily sold
and then one being heavily bought so
let's create an indicator and all we
need to do if we're confident that our
our ratio from the student T
distribution is always going to be
between zero and one then what we can do
is we can take that array multiply it by
two minus one and we're actually going
to get values normalized values between
-1 and 1. so we can also for probably
calculate a moving average of this
particular indicator so here I've got a
moving average
um that takes an indicator as the pandas
series and then we assign a number which
is that look back period and essentially
here I've got a moving average of this
bvc indicator that I've created
um which is going to look back 10
periods now we can clean up our findings
and I've just printed the last ten
thousand dollars is all of the data
points and here you can see what what
the results are here I've plotted in the
bars I've got our bvc if it was positive
for the indicator it's in blue if it was
negative then it was so heavily sold
then it was in red and you can see how
these kind of things align with the
option price which is uh in black there
over the cumulative bars index so the
number of trades or the cumulative
volume depending on which bars you've
used we use ticks here so the number of
Trades is the cumulative number trades
on the bottom
so here I've got that moving average and
potentially you could use this moving
average in an algorithm which uh you
know tries to say whether something is
really overbought and there's momentum
um in trading activity potentially
indicating trade informed trading
decisions
um and therefore potentially if you're a
market maker you might start retreating
um your bids or offers in correspondence
to that and that's where you see the
market spread increase now this is just
an illustrative example of what this
algorithm is attempting to do to show
informed trading decisions in future
videos we're going to take a look at how
you can actually relate this to the
spread and then what that means for
market makers so again algorithms like
this can really help try and discern
informed trading decision
um especially by big institutions that
are trying to split orders up into
smaller packets this can be a
pre-forecast to some large price
movement so hopefully you found
interested in this I'm going to try and
use the Theta data API in the next video
and we're going to try and do real-time
streaming and relate this to real-time
streaming so if you're interested in
that sign up for the channel and if
you're interested in taking interested
in taking a look at the Theta data API
links will be in the description
[Music]
thank you